Good morning 早晨各位
I was trying to remember when's the last time I was here preaching
It's been a while
我想一下我上一次來這裡講道的時候是幾時呢?
可能已經是一段時間了
It's all exciting for me to be here
For those of you who don't know my parents grew up in Hong Kong
我很興奮可以來到這裡當中
有些如果對我不是很認識的
我的父母都是在香港長大
So I'm Cantonese
所以我是廣東人
And I feel like I'm at home when I'm here with you all
我覺得在家的樣子非常之舒服
If you could show the first slide with some pictures
The next slide
I just want to update you
Since I haven't been here for a while
And some of you might not know
My family
Next picture
You can see the Christmas picture
We just took this last month
我是給大家一個想將我最近的情況
跟大家分享一下
這個是在聖誕節的時候我們拍的照
So many of you know my wife Sherry and my son Asher
Asher is now 13 years old and in 7th grade
我的太太是Shirley
我兒子是Asher
他現在已經是七年級13歲
And also many of you might know we are a foster family
And right now we welcomed an 18-year-old foster son
Into our family
So he doesn't always come on Sundays
But you might see him around
我們都是有領養了一個18歲的年輕人
他不是經常來到這個教會
有時你都見到他
And also in July 2024
My mom passed away after 5 years of illness
我媽媽是在2024年就離開世
她是有5年的時間都是有病的
And I've noticed since I haven't had as much chance to practice
That my Cantonese is kind of not as good anymore
你知道我沒那麼多機會去練習的時候
所以我的廣東話不是講得那麼好
So hopefully you forgive me if I want to spend more time with you
So I can practice my tones
我希望可以用多點時間和大家一起練習我的廣東話
But today we are going to be talking about the leadership of our church
Who we call elders
我們今天會是講我們教會的領導
我們所講的長老
The Bible says that an elder is someone in the church
Who helps lead and take care of God's people
聖經上說長老就是在教會裏面
幫助帶領和照顧神的子民的人
Jesus is the head of the church
And the elders are like loving coaches
基督就是教會的頭
而長老就好像是一個有愛心的教練
Coaches who watch over the church family
And teach God's word
And show others what it looks like to follow Jesus
這個教練就是守望著教會裏面的人
教導神的話語和以他的生命
去示範怎樣去跟隨耶穌
I've been blessed to serve as an elder of this church
For the last 10 years
過去10年我很有福氣能夠在這個教會裏面擔任長老
Now we know that these next few years
will be a season of change for our church family
我們知道未來幾年
這個教會會進入一個很轉變的季節
Elder Tyke just retired from his role as elder
at the end of last year
Tyke 長老在上年底的時候就正式的退休了
That leaves us across all our congregations
with just 3 elders
我們這三個語言的堂會那裏
只剩下3個長老
And the reality is with over 500 members
or people here at T4C
there are not enough elders to lead
and to care for everyone
事實上T4C有差不多500人聚會
而長老的人是不足夠帶領和照顧這麼多人的
And it's not just elders either
並不是單單是長老
You all, we all have been praying
for a Cantonese pastor for a long time now
我們都為我們粵語部要有一個牧師討告
But our current staff
including Pastor Fred, Pastor Mike
and our children's director Jody
are all close to retirement age
但是Fred 牧師和Mike 牧師
兒童士工的主任 Jody
他們已經接近退休的年齡了
And we are also talking about church planting
我們都有討論過席堂
So we are going to need even more elders and pastors
所以我們更需要更多的長老和更多的牧者
So what does this mean?
這一切是提醒我們什麼呢?
We need leaders to step up now
我們要多些領袖去站出來
Because we are going to need more mature leaders in the coming years
所以在我們未來幾年
我們要更多的成熟的領袖
And God's vision for the church
always requires a new generation of leaders to step up
神對教會的心意
一向都是要新一代願意來裝備來服侍
So as we look at God's word this morning
I want to talk about the weight
the glorious weight and responsibility of church leadership
所以當我們今天一起打開神的話語的時候
我想講一下教會的領導
怎麼是榮耀的重責
And I want to be clear
It's not just for official elders
but for anyone God's calling to step up into leadership
不單止是正式的這個長老是任何神可以呼召的
都要能夠參與
And you might not feel like you're ready for it right now
but God is preparing you for your part in the future
你可能覺得自己未必準備好
但是神已經準備了你
將來要你成就你要盡的那個本分
Let's start with a word of prayer
我們開始我們的禱告
Our great God we worship you this morning
偉大的神我們在這裡來敬拜你
We worship you with our presence
我們用我們的來臨來敬拜你
Our attention
我們的專心
And our response to your word
我們對你的話語的回應來敬拜你
We pray that you would give us your wisdom and your peace
我們祈求你給我們智慧和平安
It's in Jesus' wonderful name that we pray
和主耶穌奇妙的名來禱告
Amen
OK, let's start by digging into our Bible verses
好,我們開始的時候
我們看看聖經裡面的經文
So starting with 1 Peter 5
彼得前書第五章
OK, there's a section here, let's see
Be shepherds of God's flock
that is under your care watching over them
not because you must
but because you are willing
as God wants you to be
not pursuing dishonest gain
but eager to serve
not lording it over those entrusted to you
but being examples to the flock
我作了長老的
作基督受苦的見證
同享後來所要顯現的榮耀的
勸你們在中間和我作長老的人
務要牧養你中間神的群羊
按著神旨意照顧他們
不是出於勉強
乃是出於甘心
也不是因為貪財
乃是出於樂意
也不要合際所託付你們的
乃是作群羊的榜樣
到你要牧長顯現的時候
你們必得
永不需嘗那榮耀的冠冕
Peter is telling the church elders
to shepherd the flock
彼得是吩咐教會的長老
要牧養這個羊群
This is a metaphor from everyday life
back in ancient world
這個比喻來自古代日常生活
Today most of us aren't farmers or shepherds
今日我們大部分人都不是農夫
都不是牧羊人
But in Peter's time
shepherds were everywhere
and everyone knew what they did
但是在彼得那個時代的時候
牧羊人是隨時都可以見到的
每個人都知道
牧羊人在做的是什麼
This is a picture actually
from when I was in the Middle East
這幅相就是當我在中東的時候
我拍的
And I learned that like
there are sheep everywhere
我學到的就是
在中東那個地方的時候
這些羊周圍都見到的
When you are driving around
there are sheep in the streets
當你在開車的時候
你看到這些羊在街上
So what is it like to be a shepherd?
作為一個牧羊人的時候會是怎樣的呢?
Okay, so guiding and feeding
第一就是引導和餵養
Shepherds spend all day
taking care of their sheep
牧羊人每天
經常都是這樣照顧牠們的羊群
They are making sure the sheep have food
and water and shelter
他們確保這個羊有食物
有水和有地方
They help to heal them
when they are injured or sick
當這個羊受傷的時候
或者生病的時候
他們會幫忙去醫治牠們
Without a shepherd
the sheep easily wander off
get lost or fall into danger
如果沒有這個羊的帶領的時候
這個羊很容易迷失
走失了或者跌下危險
Shepherds also protect their sheep
牧羊人同時保護這些羊群
They protect them from predators
and they guide them to safe pastures
牧羊人保護這些羊群
不會受到野獸的攻擊
帶牠們去安全的草場
They watch for trouble
and they stand between the sheep and harm
牧羊人留意四周圍的危險
保養這些羊群免受傷害
Shepherds also lead their sheep
牧人也是帶領這些羊群
The sheep learn the shepherd's voice
and they follow them when they are called
羊會認到牧羊人的聲音
當牧羊人被叫的時候
牧羊人會跟著牧羊人
True shepherds lead by caring relationship
not by force or by yelling
真正的牧人會用關係和關心去帶領
不是說要強迫他們
或者大聲地喝他們
You know, often in today's world
leadership is about being in charge
or being above others
你知道在現在的世界裡面
領導往往就是掌權
或者是在人的高高在上
But real leadership is about gaining trust
through love and daily presence
但是在整個國裡面
真正的領導就是保護人們
關心和服侍人
It means getting close to people
protecting, caring, serving
and guiding by example
真的是走近他們
保護他們
服侍他們
用自己的生命作為一個榜樣去帶領
And that's what Jesus as the good shepherd does for us
這就是耶穌
我們這個好牧人為我們所做的
That's what elders are called to be examples of
長老就是被呼召出來
活出這個榜樣
Shepherding is spending time with people
牧羊就是要用時間跟人一起相處
Really getting to know the church family
真正認識這個教會裡面的家人
Shepherding is walking alongside someone
through their struggles
是陪伴一個人走過他的困難
Or helping to share wisdom
for small and big decisions
或者是有大小的決定的時候
分享跟他分享的智慧
Shepherding is leading by showing
牧羊就是以身作則
Not just telling
不是就這樣用口講
It's building trust that helps the whole church
grow closer to Jesus
是建立這個信任
幫助這個教會更加親近耶穌
Right now a lot of people
are going through difficult times
現在時候可能會有很多人
是經歷到這個困難
They need shepherds to help guide them
他們需要這個牧羊人去引導他們
The next passage we'll look is from James
第二個經文我們要看的就是由雅各書
James 3.1 warns
Not many of you should become teachers
my fellow believers
because you know that
we who teach will be judged more strictly
他說三章第一節說
我們的弟兄們不要作多人的師父
因為曉得我們要受更重的判斷
Now teaching in the church
isn't just about preaching a sermon
or leading a Bible class
在教會裡面教導不是單單說道
或者是帶茶經班
It's really anytime we help someone understand
what it means to follow Jesus
是每一次當我們幫助別人
去明白怎麼樣跟隨耶穌的時候
這就是教導
Now this might happen in conversations
in your community
or small groups or everyday life
這可能是跟人聊天的時候
在小組裡面
跟人一起走的時候
或者在日常的生活裡面
Also teaching is not about status
or seeking attention
還有教導不是關於地位
或者是要被人去注意
It's about influence
and with influence comes real responsibility
教導是關於影響力
而有影響力的就有真正的責任
Elders and teachers
don't just pass on information
they help open up the Bible and say
this is what it means to follow Jesus
同時長老不是只是傳遞一個訊息
就是打開聖經的時候
然後跟人說
這樣就是跟隨耶穌
So the warning in James is that
if we get it wrong
we could mislead or wound
or confuse God's people
所以在雅各這樣警告我們的時候
就是說如果我們教錯了人的時候
就可能會誤導或者傷害
或者令神所愛的人得到困擾
And unfortunately
we see so many examples of this in the world today
在我們現在的世界的時候
我們就會看到很多這樣的例子
So called leaders and teachers
who are misleading people
有很多的教師不是真正是教錯人的
But if we get it right
但如果我們真的教到正確的時候
If we are truly teaching God's word
如果我們真的按神的話語去教人的時候
We can help people build up their faith
我們就能夠幫助他們建立信心
And encourage lifelong discipleship
又鼓勵他們一生作主的門徒
This warning in James
isn't meant to make us afraid of teaching
這個警告不是說要我們很害怕去教人
We shouldn't be afraid of helping others to grow
我們不應該害怕幫助別人在屬靈的成長
It just reminds us that God
takes what we say and what we do seriously
它只不過是提醒我們
神很認真地看我們
我們所講所做的
神會很認真地看
Because what we teach can affect people
in very real ways
因為我們所講
我們所教導的
會影響人的生命
The third passage is from James 5:14
第三個經文就是由《雅各書》第五章第十四節
James links eldership closely with pastoral care
雅各將長老的職份和牧羊的關係
緊緊地連在一起
Let me read it again
Is anyone among you sick?
Let them call the elders of the church to pray over them
and anoint them with oil in the name of the Lord
這次的經文是這麼說
你們中間有病了的
他就該請教會的長老來
他們可以奉主的名
用油抹他 為他禱告
So the word that's used for anoint here
means to rub or to pour oil on someone
在這裡「羔抹」這個字
就是用油去塗在人的身上
In biblical times
that's what people did for healing
在聖經的時代
這些人就是上堅的
用一個治療的方法
It was their medicine
這些就是他們的藥物
So James is telling the church
to gather to elders to pray
but also to care for the sick
with practical help
所以雅各祭的意思就是
要教會的長老為這些病人來禱告
同一個時候
就用實際的方法來照顧他們
就好像用藥物一樣
Sometimes we think that elders
are just meeting planners or sermon givers
有時我們以為長老就是
只不過是開會
在這裡安排一些事
或者是講一下道
But God calls elders to step into those crisis moments
但是神呼召長老在危機的時候
隨時效命
Maybe it's sitting by the hospital beds
可能在病床那裡坐在旁邊
Praying with the suffering
或者是和受苦的人一起來禱告
Caring for both spiritual and physical needs
或者是屬於身體上要照顧的軟弱的人
In those moments
the elder's job is not to be above others
在這個時候長老的角色
不是說要高高在上
But to come alongside
就是並肩而行
Not just to teach
不是說要去教導
But to come alongside in the hardships of life
是親身走入生命裡面的困難
So this extends the role of elders
beyond just preaching
所以這個是延伸到
長老的職責不是說超過教導
You might say that elders are spiritual
first responders
你可以說長老是
屬靈的第一線的回應者
And their ministry includes
both the spiritual and the physical
他們的角色是
包括了身體上和屬靈上
To model both compassion and faith
in all circumstances
無論在哪一個處境裡面
都活出這個憐憫和信心
In this way elders show
the church's care for its members
在這個方式裡面
長老就成為教會對信徒的關愛
這個具體的表現
To connect the needs of the body
to the grace and the healing of Jesus
將教會肢體裡面的需要
連結在基督的恩典和意志裡面
So that's what our three passages
are talking about today
這個就是我們三節的經文所說的
Let's talk a little bit more about
what elders are
我們說一下長老是什麼
The word that's translated as elders
in these verses is presbyterus
在聖經裡面翻譯長老這個字
就是presbyterius這個字
The word literally means elder or older one
or someone known for wisdom and maturity
聖經裡面的原意就是
這個字的原意就是年長者
或者是較成熟的人
或者是以智慧和成熟見稱的人
This message I hate to admit it
I am now an older person
我不是很想去承認
但是我已經是年紀都長了
But we can see from the Bible
from the earliest days of Israel
the God's people appointed groups of older people
older men to lead and to guide
我們看到就是早期的
以色列早期的開始的時候
神就是已經是揀選一群
年紀大的有智慧的人去帶領
There were elders who served in the Sanhedrin in Jerusalem
在耶路撒冷的公會裡面
有長老在這裡服侍
There were elders who served in the local synagogues
有不同在或者是
在地方的教會裡面
都有長老在這裡服侍
And this idea of eldership
was adopted by the first Christians
我們知道早期教會的時候
都很快地承接了這個長老的制度
The church in Jerusalem gathered elders
耶路撒冷的教會是聚集這個長老
And Paul and Barnabas made sure to
that every church they started
had its own group of elders
而保羅和巴拿巴都確保
在每一個建立這個地方教會的時候
都有一組的長老
So when scripture addresses elders
it's not just referring to a formal office
所以當聖經提到長老的時候
不是單單只是一個正式的職位
It's also inviting the older, mature and wise people
to step up in faith
都是邀請這些年紀比較大
信心成熟和有智慧的人站出來
These people are to share their guidance
their experience and their spiritual insight
with the church family
這些人站出來就是在教會裡面
分享他們的經驗
他們的屬靈的洞見
So any of you who are further along
in your faith journey
所以你們每一個在信心的路上
已經是走得很前了
Those who might be called older
年紀是比較大一點的
We need you to use your age and your wisdom
for the good of the church family
我們是要你的年紀
你的智慧來祝福整個教會
But even for those who are young
但是除了之外
就算是年紀比較輕的
The responsibilities that we just talked about
in the verses of teaching, shepherding and ministry
are to be part of our daily lives
我們剛才所講的
我們的教導、牧養、服侍
都是我們生活的每一個部分
For every maturing Christian, not just elders
是給所有成熟的信徒
不只是單單是長老
We see in the New Testament
that believers are encouraged over and over again
to love one another
我們在新約裏面我們看到
一再二再而三這樣去
鼓勵我們彼此去相愛
To encourage one another with the truth
是用這個真理去鼓勵大家
To care for each other's needs
彼此照顧
To serve one another
彼此去服侍
So we want all believers
to do those things that we just talked about
所以我們想所有的信徒
都做這些以上我所講的東西
So eldership really is
part of the maturing process of every Christian
所以這個長老都是
我們每一個信徒成熟的過程裏面
都出現的
And as we look for elders
we're not just saying "you" or "you"
當我們去選長老的時候
我們不是就這樣說
是你是你
We're looking for those who are already
exhibiting these characteristics
我們是去選一些
已經展示出這些特質的人
So I think in God's plan for the church
each one of us should be growing
in all of these abilities
我覺得我們每一個人
都應該在這方面
在這些本能方面
繼續在這裏成長
To shepherd others
去牧養別人
To teach others
去教導別人
To minister to others
去服侍別人
OK
There was a lot of me talking just now
剛才你聽過我講了很多樣東西
I want you to take some time to think about
how it applies to your life
我想你們想一下
怎樣將我所講的東西
是應用在你的生命裏面呢
So why don't we just take 30 seconds or so
and think about this question
我們想你用30秒的時間去想一下以下這個問題
If we are all called as Christians
to grow in teaching shepherding ministry
What is God calling you to work on right now?
如果神呼召我們要做這方面的事
教導牧養去服侍的時候
神現在是呼召你要做哪一方面呢?
And practically what steps can you take this week to practice?
還有具體方面
這個星期你可以採取什麼行動去操練和實踐以上的東西?
I want you to think about it right now for about 30 seconds
我想你用大約30秒的時間去想一下這一方面
Okay, I hope you have some ideas
我希望你們已經是有些意念
Cause we need each of you to do your part so that we can grow
我希望我們每一個都要盡我們自己的本份
讓我們教會能夠成長
We already talked about how there is not enough elders to do all the work
我們已經講過我們不夠長老去做所有的工作
We can only function as a family if everyone does their part
我們在教會裡的家庭要每個人做自己的本份
So we just talked about how everyone has a role to teach and to shepherd and to minister
我們每一個人都有一個角色去教導、去牧養和去服侍
So does that mean that I don't need to do anything as an elder?
那是不是代表我做一個長老我不需要做什麼呢?
I think what sets apart the elders is the breadth of the responsibility of their calling
我相信長老與眾不同就是長老的責任是廣闊的
Even though all of us are called to teach and to shepherd and to minister
the elders do the same things for the whole church
雖然每一個人都有一個角色去教導、牧養和去服侍
但是長老是為整個教會來服侍的
The elders' teaching must faithfully guide the congregations in truth
長老的教導都是要在真理裡面引導整個教會
The elders' shepherding extends to all kinds of needs for all members
他們的牧養是伸延到所有弟兄姊妹各種不同的需要
And the elders' ministry calls them to model and coordinate care for the entire body
他們的侍奉是要以自己的生命作為榜樣和協調幫助教會關顧的工作
So remember the Bible tells us that Jesus is the head of the church
聖經告訴我們基督就是教會的頭
He's the one that leads and directs and gives life to the whole body
耶穌就是帶領、指引和給生命給整個教會的群體
每一個人的領袖包括長老都可以取代這個位置
那麼長老是如何進入這個位置呢?
我們想想我們的身體
我們知道我們的頭就是給所有的指令
但我們知道我們的神經系統包括脊椎
是連結和協調我們身體每一個部份
或者作為一個例子
長老就好像一個脊椎
他們是作為一個連結和協調的工作
是幫助我們的頭和我們其他身體的部份連結在一起
所以最主要的工作不是關於權力、侍奉
而是裝備身體其他部份
是幫助每一位信徒發現他們神給他們的恩賜
在信心裏面成長
是學習如何彼此服侍
我們的教會的主題在耶福所書就是這樣
長老和牧師的角色就是裝備各位信徒
當長老有這樣的方式服侍的時候
教會就成為一個很合一的身體
每一部份都得到支持都可以裝備
所以長老不是出於權力而是出於一個牧人的心去引領
我們會有一連串的講道
是關於長老積分榮耀的重責
這個重責是什麼意思呢?
並不是說所有我們的工作、我們所有的會議
是我們要向神交代和有影響力
我們對人的靈魂、他們的信仰、他們的生命有非常大的影響力
是,神也說他們將來要在神面前交仗
這是一個非常令人驚慌但也帶有榮耀的
神竟然用我一個這麼不完善的人去服侍他,真是一個很大的榮耀
我們都很想看到將來在永恆當中你怎樣去尊崇我們的神
所以我們被呼召去做一個長老是非常之榮耀的
我們怎樣將這些應用在我們每一個人的生命裡面呢?
第一個應用是給每一位的
雖然神不是呼召我們做長老,但祂也想我們都有長老的特質
我們引導、裝備、教導、服侍、牧養
我們每一個人都要去培養這些特質
當我們這樣做的時候,整個教會是會興旺的
我們第二個應用是不要等,我們開始去帶領
我們當中有很多人已經有神給這些恩賜
我們可以用這些恩賜在正常的環境裡面或平時
我們有很多的侍奉,例如在兒童的侍工裡面,主日學裡面,崇拜裡面,都要很多人的侍奉
或者你可以請一些人來到你家裡一起吃東西
如果你看見有人受傷,你可以在他旁邊安慰他
或者你可以發一些郵件給他,鼓勵他,幫助他
第三個應用就是我們可以踏上長老的呼召
當中有神正在呼召你踏上長老的角色
不要讓猶豫或者害怕來阻止你
做一個長老並不是代表我有所有的答案
並不是要做一個十全十美的信徒
是有一個願意去服事,願意去聆聽的心
如果你有這個感受,你可以跟長老或牧師說一下
你知道,我們的教會正在等待一個廣東話的牧師
我想再次提醒大家,聖經中的模式就是領袖可以從教會裡面被認出
如果我們當中有一個人走出來,去受裝備成為我們語言部的牧師的時候,真是一個很大的祝福
如果你想走這條路的時候,我們知道整個教會會幫助你
會支持你和裝備你
我也為這件事而禱告,希望神會呼召你願意踏出這個信心的一步
或者我可以比較精準一點
或者你會說我是一個很年輕的信徒或初信,我可以做些什麼呢?
我們可以學習,可以看看神給你的恩賜是什麼
或者你可以想一下你怎樣去服事我們整個的教會
可能會為人煮一餐飯,或者打電話給人
或者人有困難的時候,你在他旁邊安慰
你可以想一下你怎樣可以成長
每一天的榜樣,比你說什麼話都更有力量
父母就是他們家庭裡面的長老
不斷地牧養他們
如果是有經驗和成熟的信徒
你累積來的跟隨耶穌就給了你很多智慧
我30年前來到明州
我是很年輕的
你們很多服事我
很多我都叫你們做叔叔或姨姨
需要你去帶領這個教會
在我結束之前,我有以下的問題想大家去思考
今天耶穌作為教會的頭
祂呼召你擔任將來什麼樣的角色
你可以教導牧養或服事哪一個人
或者我們可以用30秒的時間去思考這個問題
你向你周圍的人告訴他們你的角色是什麼
我們在這裡停,你可以繼續談,但我們暫時在這裡停
我們在結束今天的講道
這個就成為我們今天的挑戰
耶穌已經呼召我們去跟隨祂
祂已經準備了我們有善功,影響力和人際的關係
讓我們能夠在祂的國度裡帶有影響力
你怎樣可以繼續成長在教會裡做你要做的角色呢
我們希望你盡你的本份,無論是在團體裡,還是在教會裡的其他工作
領導不是只是給少數的人
這是我們很自然的一個部分,當我們是一個成長的門徒的時候
希望各位願意踏出這一步,站出來成為教會的領導
我們做一個結束的禱告
主我們感謝祢,不單是呼召我們去領受祢的愛
也呼召我們去分享祢的愛,去服事、去教導和關懷別人
幫助我們在成長的生命裡繼續成長,去祝福別人和去尊榮我們的耶穌
奉耶穌基督的名
Amen